 // To link play button active to circle animation -----------------
let circle = document.querySelector(".circle");
let play = document.querySelector(".playButton")
play.onclick = function () {
    circle.classList.toggle('active');
}



// Questions ------------------------------------------------------
const allQuestions = [
    [
        {"letter": "A", "question": "A foreigner, or someone who comes from another planet.", "answer": "alien"},
        {"letter": "A", "question": "Someone who performs in a play or in a film.", "answer": "actor"},
        {"letter": "A", "question": "A place where a plane comes in to land.", "answer": "airport"}
    ],
    [
        {"letter": "B", "question": "A place where you can deposit money.", "answer": "bank"},
        {"letter": "B", "question": "The colour of the sky at night.", "answer": "black"},
        {"letter": "B", "question": "This appears if you cut yourself.", "answer": "blood"}
    ],
    [
        {"letter": "C", "question": "A family pet who might chase birds and mice.", "answer": "cat"},
        {"letter": "C", "question": "When two cars bang into each other it causes this.", "answer": "crash"},
        {"letter": "C", "question": "A vegetable that is orange in colour.", "answer": "carrot"}
    ],
    [
        {"letter": "D", "question": "A large animal that lives in a cave and breathes fire", "answer": "dragon"},
        {"letter": "D", "question": "Something that you call eating after seven o'clock.", "answer": "dinner"},
        {"letter": "D", "question": "A white bird that is a symbol of peace.", "answer": "dove"}
    ],
    [
        {"letter": "E", "question": "A large animal that has a very big nose.", "answer": "elephant"},
        {"letter": "E", "question": "The most spoken language in the world.", "answer": "english"},
        {"letter": "E", "question": "London is the capital city of this country.", "answer": "england"}
    ],
    [
        {"letter": "F", "question": "The last day of the working week.", "answer": "friday"},
        {"letter": "F", "question": "Opposite of slow.", "answer": "fast"},
        {"letter": "F", "question": "A person that you can talk to, spend time with, and share things with.", "answer": "friend"}
    ],
    [
        {"letter": "G", "question": "The opposite of 'rough'.", "answer": "gentle"},
        {"letter": "G", "question": "Someone who eats too much is this.", "answer": "greedy"},
        {"letter": "G", "question": "The opposite of 'stop'.", "answer": "go"}
    ],
    [
        {"letter": "H", "question": "You need this to pump blood around your body.", "answer": "heart"},
        {"letter": "H", "question": "Something that sits on top of your shoulders.", "answer": "head"},
        {"letter": "H", "question": "You wear this on your head!", "answer": "hat"}
    ],
    [
        {"letter": "I", "question": "A European county. Its capital cty is Rome.", "answer": "italy"},
        {"letter": "I", "question": "A piece of land surrounded by the sea.", "answer": "island"},
        {"letter": "I", "question": "A country near to the UK. Its capital city is Dublin.", "answer": "ireland"}
    ],
    [
        {"letter": "J", "question": "Trousers; usually made of denim.", "answer": "jeans"},
        {"letter": "J", "question": "The first month of the year.", "answer": "january"},
        {"letter": "J", "question": "The most used programming language in the world.", "answer": "javascript"}
    ],
    [
        {"letter": "K", "question": "You use this to boil water in the kitchen to make a cup of tea.", "answer": "kettle"},
        {"letter": "K", "question": "A unit of weight in the metric system.", "answer": "kilo"},
        {"letter": "K", "question": "The husband of a queen.", "answer": "king"}
    ],
    [
        {"letter": "L", "question": "This is what you get when you borrow money from the bank.", "answer": "loan"},
        {"letter": "L", "question": "A machine to carry people up and down floors in a bulding.", "answer": "lift"},
        {"letter": "L", "question": "A large vehicle used for transporting goods.", "answer": "lorry"}
    ],
    [
        {"letter": "M", "question": "Pork, beef, chicken and ham are all types of this.", "answer": "meat"},
        {"letter": "M", "question": "If you can remember a lot of things you have a good...", "answer": "memory"},
        {"letter": "M", "question": "You spend this at the shops.", "answer": "money"}
    ],
    [
        {"letter": "N", "question": "Preposition. The opposite of far.", "answer": "near"},
        {"letter": "N", "question": "Opposite of day.", "answer": "night"},
        {"letter": "N", "question": "The opposite of 'always'.", "answer": "never"}
    ],
    [
        {"letter": "O", "question": "The frst number.", "answer": "one"},
        {"letter": "O", "question": "A bird that likes to place it's head in the sand.", "answer": "ostrich"},
        {"letter": "O", "question": "A fruit and a colour.", "answer": "orange"}
    ],
    [
        {"letter": "P", "question": "Something that you open on your birthday.", "answer": "present"},
        {"letter": "P", "question": "The leader of a republican county.", "answer": "president"},
        {"letter": "P", "question": "Something that you can hang on your wall at home.", "answer": "pictures"}
    ],
    [
        {"letter": "Q", "question": "You stand in this when you wait in line at a supermarket.", "answer": "queue"},
        {"letter": "Q", "question": "The wife of a king.", "answer": "queen"},
        {"letter": "Q", "question": "What I'm asking you now!", "answer": "question"}
    ],
    [
        {"letter": "R", "question": "A colour that symbolises the Communist party.", "answer": "red"},
        {"letter": "R", "question": "A white coloured food commonly eaten in Asia.", "answer": "rice"},
        {"letter": "R", "question": "A flower that has sharp thorns.", "answer": "rose"}
    ],
    [
        {"letter": "S", "question": "The name of woolly animals who love to eat grass.", "answer": "sheep"},
        {"letter": "S", "question": "Men do this to their face.", "answer": "shave"},
        {"letter": "S", "question": "A place in the garden where you can keep tools and a lawnmower.", "answer": "storage"}
    ],
    [
        {"letter": "T", "question": "Me, Mrs, Ms, Dr, and Rev are all examples of this.", "answer": "title"},
        {"letter": "T", "question": "Someone who repairs clothes.", "answer": "tailor"},
        {"letter": "T", "question": "A type of shoe that is worn for running or playing sports.", "answer": "trainers"}
    ],
    [
        {"letter": "U", "question": "Opposite of happy.", "answer": "unhappy"},
        {"letter": "U", "question": "You need this when it rains.", "answer": "umbrella"},
        {"letter": "U", "question": "The brother of someoneâ€™s mother or father.", "answer": "uncle"}
    ],
    [
        {"letter": "V", "question": "A city in Italy that is famous for its canals.", "answer": "venice"},
        {"letter": "V", "question": "A sour tasting flavouring.", "answer": "vinegar"},
        {"letter": "V", "question": "A person who cures animals.", "answer": "vet"}
    ],
    [
        {"letter": "W", "question": "A season. In England it is cold and frosty.", "answer": "winter"},
        {"letter": "W", "question": "Opposite of dry.", "answer": "wet"},
        {"letter": "W", "question": "A drink that is made from grapes. Can be red or white.", "answer": "wine"}
    ],
    [
        {"letter": "X", "question": "You are called this if you have special mutant abilities.", "answer": "x-man"},
        {"letter": "X", "question": "Another name for a photocopy.", "answer": "xerox"},
        {"letter": "X", "question": "A musical instrument made up of metal or wooden bars.", "answer": "xylophone"}
    ],
    [
        {"letter": "Y", "question": "Something you say to agree with people.", "answer": "yes"},
        {"letter": "Y", "question": "The colour ofthe sun.", "answer": "yellow"},
        {"letter": "Y", "question": "Found in the middle of an egg.", "answer": "yolk"}
    ],
    [
        {"letter": "Z", "question": "A black and white animal.", "answer": "zebra"},
        {"letter": "Z", "question": "A place where exotic animals are kept in a city.", "answer": "zoo"},
        {"letter": "Z", "question": "Something you find on a pair of trousers.", "answer": "zip"}
    ],
        
];



// DOM declarations ------------------------------------------------
const nameContainer = document.querySelector('.nameContainer');
const nameField = document.querySelector('#nameField');

const timerField = document.querySelector('.timerField')
const timer = document.querySelector('#timer')

const numberOfCorrectField = document.querySelector('.numberOfCorrectField')
const numberOfCorrect = document.querySelector('#numberOfCorrect')

const textMessage = document.querySelector('.textMessage');
const messageToUser = document.querySelector('#messageToUser');
const correct = document.querySelector('#strongCheems');
const incorrect = document.querySelector('#cryingCheems');

const pasapalabraContainer = document.querySelector('.pasapalabraContainer');
const question = document.querySelector('#question');
const answerField = document.querySelector('#answerField');

const rankingContainer = document.querySelector('.rankingContainer');
const rankingTable = document.querySelector('#rankingTable');
const rankingText = document.querySelector('#rankingText');



// User's Name Stage -----------------------------------------------
let userName;

nameField.addEventListener("keyup", function(event) {
    if (event.key === "Enter") {         // => If Enter key was hit
        userName = nameField.value.charAt(0).toUpperCase() + nameField.value.slice(1);
        messageToUser.textContent = "Welcome " + userName + "!\nGet ready to play\nthe game";
        nameField.readOnly = true;

        decidingQuestions();
        nameTransitions();
        countdownTimer();
    }
});



// Pasapalabra Game ------------------------------------------------
let thisGameQuestions;

const decidingQuestions = () => {
    thisGameQuestions = [];
    for (let i in allQuestions) {
        let chosenQuestion = Math.floor(Math.random()*3);
        thisGameQuestions.push({
            "letter": allQuestions[i][chosenQuestion]["letter"], 
            "question": allQuestions[i][chosenQuestion]["question"], 
            "answer": allQuestions[i][chosenQuestion]["answer"], 
            "answered": false, 
            "guessedRight": undefined
        });
    }
    console.log(thisGameQuestions);
}

let answer;
let letterCount = 0;

const showQuestion = () => {
    if (letterCount === 26) {
        letterCount = 0;
    }

    document.querySelector(`#letter${letterCount}`).style.transition = "0.5s";
    
    if (thisGameQuestions[letterCount]["answered"] === false) {
        question.textContent = `${thisGameQuestions[letterCount]["letter"]} - ${thisGameQuestions[letterCount]["question"]}`;
        document.querySelector(`#letter${letterCount}`).style.background = "white";
        document.querySelector(`#alphabet${letterCount}`).style.color = "black";
        document.querySelector(`#letter${letterCount}`).style.borderColor = "black";
    } else {
        letterCount +=1;
        showQuestion();  
    }
}

answerField.addEventListener("keyup", function(event) {
    if (event.key === "Enter") {
        answer = answerField.value.toLowerCase();
        
        if (answer === "pasapalabra") {
            messageToUser.textContent = "Passed";
            transitionIfPassed();
        } else if (answer === "end") {
            messageToUser.textContent = "Finsihing...";
            transitionIfEnd();
        } else if (answer === thisGameQuestions[letterCount]["answer"]) {
            messageToUser.textContent = "Correct!"
            transitionIfCorrect();
            thisGameQuestions[letterCount]["answered"] = true;
            thisGameQuestions[letterCount]["guessedRight"] = true;
        } else {
            messageToUser.textContent = "Wrong! The correct\nanswer is " + thisGameQuestions[letterCount]["answer"].toUpperCase();
            transitionIfIncorrect();
            thisGameQuestions[letterCount]["answered"] = true;
            thisGameQuestions[letterCount]["guessedRight"] = false;
        }

        answerField.value = "";
        
        answersAndCorrect();
        if (countAnswered === 26) {
            answer = "end";
        }

        if (answer !== "end") {
            letterCount += 1;
            showQuestion();
        }

        if (answer === "end") {
            timeLeft = 0;
        }
    }
});

let countAnswered;
let countCorrect;

const answersAndCorrect = () => {
    countAnswered = 0;
    countCorrect = 0;

    for (let i in thisGameQuestions) {
        if (thisGameQuestions[i]["answered"] === true) {
            countAnswered += 1;
        }
        
        if (thisGameQuestions[i]["answered"] === true) {
            countCorrect += 1;
        }
    }

    numberOfCorrect.textContent = countCorrect;
}

let timeLeft = 153;
const countdownTimer = () => {
    setInterval( function(){
        if (timeLeft === 0){
            transitionIfEnd();
            rankings();
        }
        timer.textContent = timeLeft;
        timeLeft -= 1;
    }, 1000);
}



// Rankings --------------------------------------------------------
let rankingList = [
    {"player": "Gerard Way", "guessedRight": 23},
    {"player": "Billy Joe", "guessedRight": 6},
    {"player": "Amy Lee", "guessedRight": 13},
    {"player": "Kurt Cobain", "guessedRight": 15},
    {"player": "Serj Tankian", "guessedRight": 17},
    {"player": "Dolores O'Riordan", "guessedRight": 20},
];

let rankingMessage;

const rankings = () => {
    if (countAnswered === 26) {
        updateList();
        rankingText.textContent = `You guessed ${countCorrect} words right\nout of ${countAnswered} questions answered.`;

    } else if (answer === "end" && countAnswered !== 26){
        rankingShow();
        rankingText.textContent = `You guessed ${countCorrect} words right\nout of ${countAnswered} questions answered.\nTho not finishing the game won't let you\ntake place in the rankings.`;

    } else if (answer !== "end" && countAnswered !== 26) {
        rankingShow();
        rankingText.textContent = `Time has finished.\nBy not finishing the game,\nyou can't appear in the rankings.`;
    }

    rankingTable.textContent = rankingMessage.join("\n");
}

const updateList = () => {
    rankingList.push( {"player": userName, "guessedRight": countCorrect});
    rankingShow();

    rankingMessage[0] = "The updated ranking is:";

}

const rankingShow = () => {
    rankingList.sort((a,b) => b.guessedRight - a.guessedRight);

    rankingMessage = ["The current ranking is:"];
    for (let i = 0 ; i < rankingList.length ; i++) {
        rankingMessage.push(`${i+1}: ${rankingList[i]["player"]} guessed ${rankingList[i]["guessedRight"]} questions right.`);
    }
}



// Transitions -----------------------------------------------------
const nameTransitions = () => {
    textMessage.style.opacity = 1;
    textMessage.style.visibility = "visible";

    setTimeout(function() {
        nameContainer.style.transition = "1s";
        nameContainer.style.opacity = 0;
        nameContainer.style.visibility = "hidden";
        textMessage.style.opacity = 0;
        textMessage.style.visibility = "hidden";
    },3000);
    
    setTimeout(function() {
        showQuestion();
        pasapalabraContainer.style.opacity = 1;
        pasapalabraContainer.style.visibility = "visible";
        answerField.style.opacity = 1;
        answerField.style.visibility = "visible";
        timerField.style.opacity = 1;
        timerField.style.visibility = "visible";
        numberOfCorrectField.style.opacity = 1;
        numberOfCorrectField.style.visibility = "visible";
    }, 4000);
}

const transitionIfPassed = () => {
    document.querySelector(`#letter${letterCount}`).style.background = "radial-gradient(circle, rgba(0,211,255,1) 0%, rgba(32,112,150,1) 74%, rgba(28,49,98,1) 100%)";
    document.querySelector(`#alphabet${letterCount}`).style.color = "white";
    document.querySelector(`#letter${letterCount}`).style.borderColor = "white";
    messageToUser.style.color = "white";
    textMessage.style.left = "12rem";
    messageToUser.style.left = "7rem";
    textMessage.style.opacity = 1;
    textMessage.style.visibility = "visible";
    correct.style.opacity = 1;
    correct.style.visibility = "visible";
    
    setTimeout(function() {
        textMessage.style.opacity = 0;
        textMessage.style.visibility = "hidden";
        correct.style.opacity = 0;
        correct.style.visibility = "hidden";
    },2000);
}

const transitionIfCorrect = () => {
    document.querySelector(`#letter${letterCount}`).style.background = "rgb(34, 192, 34)";
    document.querySelector(`#alphabet${letterCount}`).style.color = "white";
    document.querySelector(`#letter${letterCount}`).style.borderColor = "white";
    messageToUser.style.color = "rgb(34, 192, 34)";
    textMessage.style.left = "12rem";
    messageToUser.style.left = "7rem";
    textMessage.style.opacity = 1;
    textMessage.style.visibility = "visible";
    correct.style.opacity = 1;
    correct.style.visibility = "visible";
    
    hideMessage();
}

const transitionIfIncorrect = () => {
    document.querySelector(`#letter${letterCount}`).style.background = "red";
    document.querySelector(`#alphabet${letterCount}`).style.color = "white";
    document.querySelector(`#letter${letterCount}`).style.borderColor = "white";
    messageToUser.style.color = "red";
    textMessage.style.left = "10rem";
    messageToUser.style.left = "7rem";
    textMessage.style.opacity = 1;
    textMessage.style.visibility = "visible";
    incorrect.style.opacity = 1;
    incorrect.style.visibility = "visible";

    hideMessage();
}

const hideMessage = () => {
    setTimeout(function() {
        textMessage.style.opacity = 0;
        textMessage.style.visibility = "hidden";
        incorrect.style.opacity = 0;
        incorrect.style.visibility = "hidden";
    },2000);
}

const transitionIfEnd = () => {
    pasapalabraContainer.style.opacity = "0";
    pasapalabraContainer.style.visibility = "hidden";
    document.querySelector('#alphabet').style.transitionDelay = "2s";
    document.querySelector('#alphabet').style.opacity = "0";
    document.querySelector('#alphabet').style.visibility = "hidden";
    timerField.style.opacity = 0;
    timerField.style.visibility = "hidden";
    numberOfCorrectField.style.opacity = 0;
    numberOfCorrectField.style.visibility = "hidden";
    
    rankingContainer.style.visibility = "visible";
    rankingContainer.style.opacity = "1";
    
}

